<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The state of parties, and of the publick as influenc'd by those parties, in this conjuncture, offered to English men.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15662</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11926327</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11926327</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51030</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51030)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 515:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The state of parties, and of the publick as influenc'd by those parties, in this conjuncture, offered to English men.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51030:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The State of <hi>PARTIES,</hi> and of the <hi>PUBLICK;</hi> as influenc'd by thoſe
<hi>Parties,</hi> in this Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, offered to <hi>ENGLISH MEN.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>'TIS a miſerable Circumſtance, and the General Ruine of proſperous States, when Parties out of Separate Intereſts and Paſſions purſue different Ends of their own, without regard to the Publick, although the chief Intereſt of each: But it is a Circumſtance beyond common Miſery, a Propenſity to ruine more than natural, and a Fatality over Mankind, greater than has been ever obſerved, perhaps, in any Country or Set of Men, that they ſhould be divided into Parties from the Publick Intereſt, when there is not ſo much as any <hi>real</hi> particular Intereſt, <hi>in effect,</hi> carrying on in any of thoſe different Parties; not any of theſe diſcriminating Intereſts <hi>ſo laid,</hi> or <hi>ſo purſued,</hi> as that, by all the violent Steps taken by the Engagers, they are any ways ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced: So that although Violence be done, and ſtill doing perpetually to the Publick; though all contend for the Promotion of that Intereſt or Party under which they <hi>only</hi> look for any Happineſs; Yet for all this,
<hi>not one</hi> of theſe Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts receive any Advantage; not one of theſe Parties are likely to procure or come any thing near their End.</p>
            <p>Our Nation muſt be allowed to be in a moſt compleat way to Miſery, if this be proved their Caſe.</p>
            <p>That there are Parties is well known. The firſt great Diviſion is between King
<hi>William</hi> and King <hi>James;</hi> which takes in all our preſent active Men: For as for
<hi>Commonwealth's-men,</hi> which ſome would have to be a <hi>third</hi> Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; beſides the Turn it ſerves at Court, it has no meaning; unleſs the quiet Part of
<hi>England,</hi> thoſe tired with Revolutions, and farther Engagements with Men of theſe Days, or thoſe that are divided in their Thoughts upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of either King, as they ſtand to <hi>England;</hi> unleſs, I ſay, theſe be they call'd <hi>Commonwealth's-men,</hi> however abſurd it be.</p>
            <p>Of theſe <hi>two</hi> Intereſts, that of King <hi>James</hi>'s does properly make but
<hi>one</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though the other <hi>two.</hi> Thoſe, I ſay, make but one Party, as they act in the Publick: for they having in Proſpect <hi>only,</hi> and as the End of all their Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Government of King <hi>James;</hi> they are not <hi>now</hi> divided, nor can be
<hi>yet,</hi> whilſt unprevailing, in any Diſpute or Difference conſiderable about Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, as <hi>how,</hi> by <hi>whom,</hi> or in what Methods, favouring one or other Party,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51030:2"/>that Government ſhall be carried on. The ſide, <hi>then,</hi> of the now-governing King being divided into <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory,</hi> there are but <hi>three</hi> Parties that pull different ways, or with any noted Force in the Publick Affairs.</p>
            <p>The meaning of all theſe Men, if they have their main Intereſt, their Stake, Eſtate and Friends, in <hi>England,</hi> is and muſt be to preſerve <hi>England,</hi> though not from perfect Monarchy, and <hi>abſolute Power</hi> of a Crown <hi>at home,</hi> (which ſome approve of, and like the beſt, whatever Name of Tyranny or Slavery it has heretofore gone by) yet to preſerve us, at leaſt from the Yoak of <hi>Foreign Power,</hi> from being over-grown by States that are about us, and coming down from being the <hi>Principal</hi> in Power and Riches, to be the
<hi>laſt</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> or but once <hi>inferiour</hi> to any of theſe neighbouring ones, which will turn to <hi>as much,</hi> ſince it neceſſarily ſubjects us to the Miſeries of thoſe Invaſions we indured <hi>of old,</hi> as then the Common Prey of all the World, and every riſing Nation. This ſurely, whatever elſe may be <hi>his</hi> Intereſt, is the Intereſt of every indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> in all theſe Parties, to prevent: But if this be what is leaſt done; if this not only be <hi>not</hi> prevented, but be the
<hi>only</hi> thing that every Party, every Side, though not <hi>intentionally,</hi> yet
<hi>really,</hi> does draw on, advance, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, and <hi>nothing elſe,</hi> no not their
<hi>Party-Intereſt,</hi> not any valuable Victory or Triumph that <hi>one</hi> may gain above
<hi>another,</hi> ſo much as gratifying a Paſſion; Then are we in that State I mention'd; in the faireſt, moſt miraculous way that can be thought on to every thing that can be call'd Ruine or Deſtruction to a Country.</p>
            <p>That when we loſe our Strength, we are more miſerable than any other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the ſureſt Seat of the moſt various, ſharp and laſting War, Experience the moſt remarkable that ever was, has taught us, from the higheſt Remembrance of our ſelves through Romans, Danes, Saxons, and many Nations more (though leſs remark'd) down to the <hi>laſt</hi> Normans, and that concluding Conqueſt which by the Power of the Conqueror abroad, and the Continuance of his Line here, eſtabliſhed us on our own Bottom. And that this was not meer Misfortune, but that it is a Fate peculiar to <hi>us,</hi> I mean, that it is a natural Evil to <hi>us</hi> more than any Country, when we are low, who ever ſtudies <hi>our Situation,</hi> and the Growths of Nations on the Continent, will know, <hi>that</hi> ſuch a Country as this is more diſputable than any other: <hi>that</hi> the Dominion of it cannot be ſo fixed, and the immediate Maſters of it, however powerful on the Continent, not able to inſure to themſelves the Poſſeſſion of it, by holding it out againſt Strangers, or guarding it from their Enemy, ſo well as of other Places: <hi>that this</hi> is, in that Senſe, as a Frontier Country; with this Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that thoſe that are <hi>really</hi> Frontier Countries, though they are ſo this Day, may have the luck not to be ſo a little while after; but that this Country has always the <hi>Nature</hi> of a Frontier, ever to maintain War in it, and to be the <hi>Subject</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> of Contention amongſt thoſe that are ſtronger than it ſelf;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51030:2"/>
               <hi>when-ever ſuch there are.</hi> In fine; <hi>That</hi> as we are an Iſland, and have the Sea round us; ſo by being Maſters of that, (which is, in ſhort, by
<hi>being in the Practice of it moſt,</hi> and can be no otherwiſe) we muſt of Conſequence be the ſtrongeſt in the World, as the World is now turn'd to Navigation, and each Country by Degrees at length brought to depend abſolutely on <hi>Trade,</hi> by want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many Neceſſaries from foreign Places, which <hi>once</hi> they could live without perhaps, but
<hi>ſince</hi> cannot; nor can defend themſelves without: this being the Change that the improved Art of Navigation has made in the World; tying Countries to a reciprocal Dependency on one another for their Growths, and obliging them to <hi>ſome ſort</hi> of Correſpondency. But on the other ſide, <hi>that</hi> as we are the ſtrongeſt in Situation by being an Iſland,
<hi>the Dominion of the Sea ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be with us:</hi> ſo <hi>that</hi> being loſt to us, in any other Hands, or divided amongſt others, we are of all the moſt and worſt expoſed.</p>
            <p>This being granted, it follows, that whatever Circumſtances of ours admit other Nations,
<hi>Foreigners, whatſoever</hi> to grow, (though at the ſame time we were granted to grow too) ſo, as <hi>in Proportion,</hi> above us in <hi>Navigation and Trade;</hi> this neceſſarily ſubjects us to all the Miſeries before pointed at, and is the direct way leading to a Conſequence that is no ways to be evaded: for when that Work is done, and the Advantage once given up; what ever Party do (as they think) their Work; 'tis altogether vain to imagine that any ſuch Party, or any Party whatſoever prevailing in this Nation, or all of them united in one, can call it back, or by any Means, Arts of State, <hi>Treaties</hi> or <hi>Engagements</hi> whatſoever, to be able to turn off that inevitable Evil that muſt light on All at once. And if
<hi>this</hi> be the Conſequence of all the Actings of every one of theſe Parties at preſent; if in the ſeeking of their own Ends they are likely not ſo much to prevail either of them over another, as to reduce us into this State, this irrecoverable Conſumption and Debility, with all the Conſequences proved; then will it be found that in the Methods now taken they act conſtantly <hi>againſt,</hi> but <hi>for</hi> no Intereſt that can be called their own.</p>
            <p>All Men naturally follow their Good: and it might be well objected that it were only <hi>a Notion,</hi> and in effect impoſſible, that Men ſhould act thus, as I ſay, were it not through Ignorance; ſuch as is indeed in our Caſe, <hi>the Want of a ſufficient Conception and real Senſe at Heart, of what is the ſole Safeguard and Support of our Country;</hi> the want of truly conſidering how Matters ſtand, as to <hi>that,</hi> and how amidſt all, <hi>that</hi> is likely to be affected, which muſt (as I have ſaid) affect us, at laſt, above every thing elſe. And ſuch a Blindneſs as this it is that Men are kept in by their Paſſions, by the Heat of Party, and the Animoſity of perſonal Quarrels, or ſo that by the Reſentment of ſome preſent Uneaſineſſes, Men are hinder'd from thinking on greater Evils at ſome Diſtance off, and not yet abſolutely felt, though juſt impending.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51030:3"/>
            <p>Now to charge every Party ſingly, according to what I have ſaid, and the Imputation of Inconſiſtency that I lay on them; I inſtance firſt in thoſe, as to the Generality, who carry on King <hi>James</hi>'s Intereſt <hi>in their Endeavours,</hi> and make <hi>his</hi> Party.</p>
            <p>Firſt, then ſuppoſe that 'twere a Service to his Intereſt to have us weak at Sea, ſunk in our Trade, in Loſs of Seamen, Ships, Builders, and all Materials and Arts-men belonging; what would it avail to his Friends, (if <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> and to no others do I ſpeak) to have him here fix'd in his Government, nay fix'd even with every one's Conſent here at home; if ſuddenly we found our ſelves thus low? How ſhould we e're regain this Loſs? how e're come up again with other Nations? Will they ſtand idle; ſee us take Breath, and let us riſe; or will they ſtay for us, and ſtop ſo long as till we grow again into our Place above them? If not; how ſhall we avoid the Conſequences above ſet down, and taken (I ſuppoſe) for granted; <hi>viz.</hi> that if we loſe the Practice of the Sea, we are then revolv'd again into our <hi>old State,</hi> meer Naked Britains; his that can take us; and (according to the natural and conſtant Practice of the Sea, we are then revolv'd again into our <hi>old State,</hi> meer Naked Britains; his that can take us; and (according to the natural and conſtant Practice of Mankind) by their Station about us, and their then readier Acceſs to us than any other Place, by lying ſo <hi>fair,</hi> and ſo on all ſides <hi>open;</hi> the aſſured common
<hi>Prize</hi> that every Nation fights for, when aiming above others, or when but in the ſlighteſt Quarrel?</p>
            <p>When once the Stroak is given that brings on this Condition; when once our <hi>Naval Sinews</hi> are cut; How is it that King <hi>James</hi> ſhall be <hi>fix'd</hi> here? How is it that either
<hi>His</hi> or any Government ſhall be ſaid to be fix'd here with us; when we our ſelves,
<hi>as a People,</hi> ſhould then <hi>belong to others,</hi> or lie <hi>at Power to belong</hi> to them: which, as Mankind and States are conſtituted, is not far dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent; ſince Power to take, and taking, are in thoſe Caſes never far aſunder: and ſince Parties are now eaſily made within a Nation conſiderable enough to ſerve a turn, and for any Invaders to ground upon: and that all Invaſions, though as perfectly ſo, as thoſe of <hi>Goths</hi> or
<hi>Vandales,</hi> can be colour'd, now, with Reaſons of <hi>Religion</hi> and
<hi>Juſtice,</hi> and as though even for the very Benefit of the invaded People? For no Countries hardly now are ever conquer'd but by a Force (as <hi>Manifeſto</hi>'s and <hi>Declarations</hi> ſet forth) intended for their <hi>Relief and juſt Eſtabliſhment:</hi> And the Name of
<hi>Conqueſt,</hi> that comes to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed after full Succeſs, is found to have been preceded by, and owe its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to the very Names, however diſſonant, of
<hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> or <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort; if once we are exhauſted in a War, <hi>ſo as that our Navigating Art and all the means of it be ſhared amongſt Foreigners, and the Current of our Trade drawn into other Channels;</hi> which by no Art can be retrieved, nor any Change of Fortune; but by a turn that may give us the Advantage that we gave, and when all elſe are fighting, give us Peace; an Accident the hardlieſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51030:3"/>to imagin'd; ſince, when once weak, we are above all others the ſureſt to feel every Diſpute, and often like to be the chiefeſt Subject. If this come ever to be our Condition, as it is endeavour'd to be now made; let any Nation whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver give us, or return us a King; if this be the <hi>Terms</hi> of ſuch a Gift, (what-ever other <hi>Terms</hi> be made); if this be <hi>that</hi> that is to bring it about; any <hi>Engliſh-Man</hi> will have but a ſorry Bargain, and <hi>ſuch</hi> a King will be of little worth to <hi>us,</hi> or we to
<hi>him.</hi> Grant that the Nation we receive him from be not, in the end, upon the account of the Lowneſs we ſhall be reduc'd to, left Maſters <hi>at Sea</hi> of all the World; and grant that they were not near ſo <hi>by Land</hi> either; Yet of what benefit will <hi>this</hi> be to us? If any Benefit, it will be this; That <hi>that Way</hi> 'twill not be determin'd whoſe we ſhall be; the <hi>other Way</hi> it will: the <hi>one Way</hi> we are a Province, and muſt ſerve immediately; the <hi>other Way</hi> we remain to be fought for, and the Diſpute muſt be in our own Land, <hi>perhaps by more than two at once.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be right, then not only they who ſerve <hi>this Court</hi> in the Preſent Way, ſerve <hi>England</hi> ill, but they too who ſerve <hi>King James</hi> in ſuch a way as is ſure to ſink us; ſet any other Neighbours over us in Navigation, and do our work as to that buſineſs: They, in effect, I ſay, do nothing for themſelves as <hi>Engliſh Men,</hi> nothing for King <hi>James</hi> as an <hi>Engliſh</hi> King.</p>
            <p>But then that <hi>theſe Sort</hi> are doubly miſtaken, appears by this: For that it <hi>is not</hi> the likelieſt way to introduce King <hi>James</hi> (unleſs for <hi>England</hi> to be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely conquer'd by another Nation, be the eaſieſt way; and ſuch a Throne, ſo gain'd to him, be thought moſt valuable, and moſt <hi>a Throne.</hi>) Becauſe that if, <hi>by the Nation's Choice,</hi> he would come in, it can <hi>be only</hi> when they find an Evil in this Government greater than they felt in that they chang'd from; or that they think they <hi>would</hi> feel by his return; and <hi>then only, when</hi> the dread of <hi>that Power,</hi> that now ſupports him, hangs leſs upon them, and that they can be freed from their Jealouſy of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King of <hi>France</hi>'s governing by King
<hi>James.</hi> Now, whilſt we are loſing every day at Sea; whilſt the King of
<hi>France</hi>'s Fleets, and Privateers grow, and the Terror of this ſpreads; there can be nothing left to give a more abſolute Horror of King <hi>James</hi> than this; and when an Invaſion comes, to drive the body of the People from an <hi>Eaſineſs</hi> and
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconcernedneſs,</hi> (which otherwiſe they would be in towards any ſuch Revolution carrying on) into a very <hi>Deſperation;</hi> which will produce the <hi>uttermoſt Reſiſtance,</hi> when it may be expected they ſhould be forc'd to yield.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hint</hi> that I have given may ſhew, I think, how much the Common <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobites</hi> are beſides their Intereſt, and how well they know <hi>to wiſh</hi> as well for their King's particular Intereſt, as for the general Intereſt of their Country; and what <hi>Mighty Service</hi> they do King <hi>James,</hi> and <hi>Diſ-ſervice</hi> to King <hi>William,</hi> by their common way of Talking about the Force of <hi>France</hi> at <hi>Sea,</hi> and their Endeavours to give ſtill greater Grounds for ſuch Terror.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51030:4"/>
            <p>But to come now to the <hi>Behaviour</hi> of the other two Parties that are ſhut up within that of K. <hi>William</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>Every Body knows there are <hi>two Sorts</hi> of Men; in <hi>each</hi> of which, there are ſuch as are <hi>engag'd</hi> to K. <hi>William</hi>'s Intereſt, as <hi>abſolutely</hi> and
<hi>without reſerve,</hi> as he has required of them, or can require of them, in any proſtitute Senſe: and yet theſe Two are perpetually oppoſing one another, and make two Sides, which are commonly diſtinguiſh'd by the Names of <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory.</hi> According to the too good Succeſs that the Courtier has had; we ſee that, notwithſtanding any Intereſt that the Patriots (as many as there are) can make; and notwithſtanding <hi>that Odium</hi> which ſo many of the <hi>Court-Followers</hi> have incurr'd, yet there is ſtill this Fatality, that
<hi>Thoſe</hi> continue the mainly prevalent in each; <hi>thoſe</hi> move the Herd of both theſe Parties; <hi>thoſe</hi> have, in effect the ſway, that are with <hi>all that Latitude</hi> I have ſaid, engag'd in the Intereſt of this Court: For whoever calls this Court in queſtion; whoever doubts its good Intention to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberties and Government; whoever quotes <hi>paſt</hi> Declarations, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances a
<hi>preſent</hi> Grievance; nay, or that in Diſcourſe is but <hi>luke-warm</hi> towards the State; a Way is found (and it ſeldom fails) to make that Man ill thought of by <hi>the Herd,</hi> ſuſpected by the Vulgar of his Party, and ſhunn'd as <hi>a Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> For with one Party he is inſur'd <hi>a Commonwealth's Man,</hi> and with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>a Plain Jacobite. For what elſe ſhould he be, that acts againſt this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> Thus with one ſhort Queſtion, and that equivocal Term of <hi>Government,</hi> as it is put there, the Courtier does his buſineſs.</p>
            <p>This ſhews what is underſtood <hi>here</hi> by <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory,</hi> meaningly as the Court is prevalent over both thoſe Parties. And <hi>as thus,</hi> let us conſider how they act: whether as likely to obtain their <hi>common End</hi> in the ſupport of this Government, in the manner 'tis ſuffer'd to be carried on by them; or whether, when that's done, as likely to obtain either of them their <hi>ſeparate End,</hi> (in proſpect of which they ſo aſſiſt, and court this Government) and as likely to carry their expected <hi>Advantage over their oppoſite Party.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Tories</hi> have it for <hi>their End</hi> to ſee <hi>the Church</hi> eſtabliſh'd in as high Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er as ever; to ſee it freed from the Eye-ſore of Diſſenters and Fanaticks: to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move <hi>the ill Precedent</hi> of <hi>Scotland:</hi> to ſet up Epiſcopacy in ſuch ſtrength as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd by the Clergy-Men <hi>themſelves,</hi> to put them out of <hi>fear of every thing;</hi> and to have a King governing with as large a Prerogative as may be; but ſtill by the Means, and <hi>under the Tuition</hi> of ſuch a Church. The Whigs <hi>dread</hi> ſuch a Power in the Church, and are ſo diſatisfied with what it has of that kind al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, fearing what may come, that they expect a greater Security than is given them at preſent, that thoſe who are Diſſenters from, or under the Mark of <hi>the Church</hi> for being ill Friends to it, may never ſee <hi>It</hi> in a condition to take its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, or give them any Diſturbance. Theſe Men exclaim generally againſt all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51030:4"/>
               <hi>Arbitrary Bower,</hi> but more eſpecially <hi>That</hi> which the Church would introduce, and that their Enemies would moſt profit by.</p>
            <p>Neither of theſe two Parties, towards the Satisfaction they deſire, go now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the making of any new Laws, or attempt any Alteration in the Preſent Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement: But their Labour is, the
<hi>gaining of the King,</hi> and the getting thoſe of their Fraternity (what-ever otherwiſe they be) into the Government. This is the only Means by which they, at this time, think to ſerve their Intereſt. This is the only Pledg they now ask for the Succeſs of their reſpective Parties; <hi>Each</hi> promiſing to themſelves that within a little, or when-ever his Majeſty has made an end of his Enemies, He will declare for <hi>them,</hi> and for the future employ on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Men <hi>of their Stamp.</hi> Now, though all this while, according to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods kept up between theſe two Parties, the Government <hi>were</hi> like to ſtand, yet it is ridiculous and fooliſh what <hi>either</hi> of theſe Men expect.</p>
            <p>We may, I think, be ſatisfied that (what-ever we may expect from any other) this
<hi>Court</hi> is not likely to be at a ſtand, and reſt contented with the allotted Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue and Prerogative; much leſs to agree to a Diminution of either; though there be a conſiderable Party in <hi>England</hi> that think, and will ſtill think, (which will coſt the Court ſome Oppoſition) that the Prerogative is at a height in ſome Points very prejudicial to
<hi>England,</hi> and likely to overturn the Ancient Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, one time or other; eſpecially, ſince the Nobility is now ſo ſunk from what it formerly ever was. It muſt therefore be ſuppos'd, that when this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Victory is obtain'd, and King <hi>William</hi> is eſtabliſh'd, either he will be <hi>immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately Abſolute,</hi> and have it in his Power to act as he fancies, or he will be as he now is, <hi>under the Reſtraint of Laws,</hi> and Parliaments to be ſtruggled with. If it be <hi>the Firſt;</hi> What is it that will move his Fancy towards the <hi>Church-Men,</hi> when under no Obligation, to reverſe all the
<hi>Scotiſh</hi>-Affairs; act contrary to the Principle of <hi>Holland,</hi> and all his Proteſtant <hi>Calviniſt</hi> Acquaintance and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>abroad,</hi> and exaſperate ſo great a Body as the Diſſenters and Whigs <hi>here?</hi> The Church-Men muſt be wonderfully conceited, and have a ſtrange good Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of themſelves, or a very wrong one of the King's Principle and Conſcience, to think He would be thus ſerviceable to them out of
<hi>Affection meerly.</hi> On the other ſide; If the Court be not (by being fully Abſolute) freed from theſe Reſtraints, but be to work its way through, and that the Prerogative be in a craving State, and wants to gain upon the People, What can more ſatisfy <hi>it</hi> than the preſent Conſtruction of <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory</hi> in Parliament? Is there any thing that the Court cannot carry? Whereas, if <hi>one</hi> Party were declar'd for, it would <hi>not</hi> be ſo. As to the <hi>Whigs,</hi> the thing is the ſame. This <hi>Ballance</hi> that the Court has got is too uſeful, and ſhall never be departed from, (ſo as that the Whigs ſhall be a jot more advanc'd) whilſt the Court muſt uſe a Parliament: and if that time once come to be
<hi>over,</hi> though it is not to be thought that the Court will <hi>ever</hi> act for the zealous Church-Men according to their Expectations, as above mention'd; yet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51030:5"/>on the other ſide, to think that then any thing will be done more for the Whigs, for the Advancement of their <hi>Perſons,</hi> or in favour of their <hi>Principles,</hi> is what the leaſt of all can be imagin'd, and is the moſt abſurd.</p>
            <p>Thus, <hi>as a Party,</hi> not either of them are likely to obtain their Ends: but their Contention to be ſtill improv'd againſt themſelves, and they made Acceſſaries in their own private Loſs; as ſubject to all the Inconveniences of ſuch a conſtant Feud, without prevailing any thing by it: And, <hi>as Engliſh-Men,</hi> inſtead of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting themſelves, they are only like to be made Acceſſaries alſo in the general Publick Loſs, which we ſhall ſuffer <hi>as a free People,</hi> by loſing all our Privileges; and <hi>as a People,</hi> by falling, at length, under Foreign Subjection, and all the Miſeries that make
<hi>even that State</hi> worſe to <hi>us</hi> than other Countries.</p>
            <p>But to know this laſt; Why this Government cannot ſtand upon its preſent Baſis (which it is ſo unlikely to change;) nor the Methods ſucceeds that <hi>the Parties</hi> take to ſupport us by this Court againſt our Enemies; why <hi>even this</hi> is truly impracticable; ſo as that
<hi>they</hi> will prove <hi>in the very utmoſt</hi> diſappointed: We muſt conſider what it is that the Court <hi>Does,</hi> and <hi>intends to do;</hi> and what means the Parties approve, or admit of, in the Court, to carry on this War, in order to ſubdue the Enemy, obtain the Peace requir'd, and ſettle <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo as that we, with the other States of <hi>Europe,</hi> may not fear <hi>one common Enemy;</hi> nor we, <hi>ſingly here,</hi> an Enemy either ſecret or open, that may undermine or ruine <hi>us alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The purpoſe of this Government, the Conditions on which it roſe, and the Ends for which it was erected, are known to be; For the reſcuing us from a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Crown, advanc'd by evil Miniſters and corrupt Judges, to be Superior to all our Laws; To ſecure us from ſuch an Inſatiableneſs of Prerogative as would ſwallow Liberty and Property, and take away the Privileges of the Subject; To free us even from ſuch a <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> of a Court as could not but tend to this Effect, and from <hi>ſuch a Miniſtry</hi> as nothing elſe could be expected under, <hi>at any time:</hi> And laſtly, To remove <hi>that</hi> under which all Laws and Conſtitutions can make but a ridiculous Safety for us; to remove, I ſay, <hi>a ſtanding Army.</hi> This being ſo; I ſay it is impoſſible to think how this Government can ſtand, if theſe Ends are not anſwer'd; except it fix it ſelf here by abſolute Conqueſt; which cannot be but with a Foreign Help: and <hi>that</hi> reduces the thing to this; That <hi>we muſt be a Province to that Prince or State that is in the greateſt Power abroad;</hi> however we may pleaſe our ſelves with calling this <hi>our own</hi> Government, or <hi>our</hi> King that then ſhall govern us.</p>
            <p>I ſay, though this Government could free it ſelf from the Enemy it is now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd with; yet, not anſwering its Ends, as above-mention'd; but directly on the contrary, purſuing thoſe others it was ſet up in oppoſition to, and ſo (as I may call it) ſubverting its own Foundation, it cannot ſtand: For if the Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Force and Power of <hi>a dreaded Neighbour</hi> be no longer on foot, ſo as to fright Men (as at preſent) into the ſupport of this Government
<hi>at any rate
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51030:5"/>or proſpect;</hi> nor that a Foreign Force, in the hands of theſe Governours, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power and conquer us; 'Tis not to be thought, that <hi>the Spirit and Principle</hi> that brought in this Government, through all the Impediments of a then ſo heightned Prerogative, and of Paſſive-Obedience Principles, that are ſo much levell'd ſince that time; 'Tis ſcarce to be imagin'd, I ſay, that <hi>that Spirit</hi> of Impatience againſt a Government, ſetting up the enſlaving Attempts and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, ſhould be <hi>ſo ſunk,</hi> againſt that comes, (when it has had, all this while, ſuch Means <hi>of growing</hi>) as that it could not make its way towards a <hi>new Change,</hi> and act <hi>another Revolution;</hi> when the
<hi>ſame Need,</hi> with an <hi>additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Reſentment and Shame</hi> for having been abus'd, together with a <hi>readier Means,</hi> and the Way ſo much facilitated by the foregoing Precedent, <hi>invites them to it.</hi> Or, if by themſelves the <hi>Party for Liberty</hi> and the <hi>Diſcontented</hi> would not be able; yet whilſt there was any of the <hi>excluded Branch</hi> remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they would by <hi>that means</hi> make an Effort which would perpetually ſhake, if not quickly overturn, this Government.</p>
            <p>But that we may prove, how that but to get through their preſent Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and reduce the Power of <hi>France,</hi> is a Work but vainly expected from this Government in the Poſture that Affairs are in; let us conſider how this War is manag'd; How our Adminiſtration ſtands in reſpect of it; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at our rate, we can ſo much as continue a defenſive War.</p>
            <p>Let us compute what are the Expences of the Nation in this War: <hi>What</hi> are the
<hi>Loſſes and Charges</hi> we ſuffer by it; and <hi>what</hi> are the <hi>Reparations</hi> we make our ſelves, by the Prejudice drawn from thence to the Enemy.</p>
            <p>Our Loſſes are, the exhauſting of the Wealth, the <hi>Stock</hi> of the Nation, in the vaſt Sums drawn out from thence, for the Uſe of Foreign Countries, and the numerous Troops paid in thoſe Countries: And at the ſame time that our Suſtinence <hi>goes out,</hi> it is hindred from <hi>coming in</hi> to us; We loſing every day in <hi>Trade;</hi> the Profit of <hi>that</hi> ſtill cut from us; and that of it which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains amongſt us, turning, in a manner, againſt us; it being the <hi>Importation</hi> of Foreign Commodities that <hi>now</hi> chiefly drives it; and our own Part begun to be manag'd by Foreigners: by which means, we abandon to <hi>others</hi> what <hi>we</hi> are every day loſing in the <hi>Navigating Practice,</hi> and the <hi>breed</hi> of Sailors and other Arts-Men belonging, that ſhould be raiſing amongſt <hi>us</hi> here. And this muſt needs be ſo, ſince the <hi>French,</hi> to all Effects, <hi>in prejudice of us,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, in reality, the <hi>Maſters of the Sea,</hi> notwithſtanding that Advantage which <hi>another</hi> Providence than that of <hi>Men,</hi> gave us over them: A Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which turn'd <hi>that</hi> into a <hi>Victory</hi> on our ſide; which (according to the ſureſt Conſequences of Humane Affairs, by the whole Diſpoſition of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the Grounds, and Form of that Enterprize on foot) ſhould have prov'd the <hi>Interception</hi> and <hi>Ruine</hi> of a great part of our Fleet, and the Execution of a Deſcent which then ſurely would have made it ſelf been felt. Now, if with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51030:6"/>ſuch an Aſſiſtance of Fortune, ſo far from being ever to be hop'd again, we are not able to maintain the Sea for <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships to ſtir without being taken; that <hi>French</hi> Squadrons ſtill, Mounſieur <hi>Du-Bart,</hi> and all the other numerous Privateers, with Veſſels ſome of 50 Guns and upwards, lie in our Channel, from off
<hi>Ireland,</hi> and round our Coaſt, do what they pleaſe, take us whole Fleets of Merchant-Men together, ſupply their King largely with what they take of ours, make Fortunes for themſelves conſiderable, and enrich the Sea-Port Towns of their Country, that flouriſh now, and grow prodigiouſly with our Spoils; If this, by our Management, be <hi>now</hi> ſo, and not prevented; If it be thus <hi>now,</hi> this very Seaſon, after what has happen'd for us, How will it be <hi>henceforward?</hi> How are we like to put a ſtop to this? And if we do not put a ſtop to what <hi>already</hi> is of this kind, (though it ſhould grow <hi>no more</hi> upon us) where muſt we be within a little?</p>
            <p>Here then we ſee our <hi>Loſſes,</hi> and where our <hi>Waſting</hi> is. And as to what
<hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations</hi> it may be expected we ſhould make our ſelves; we are ſo far from aiming at the Ruine of our Enemy, or the offending of him in <hi>this</hi> way, that we are not ſo much as in any proſpect of being in a Condition of preventing that Ruine which comes in upon our ſelves <hi>this Way;</hi> though it be properly <hi>our chief</hi> and <hi>only</hi> Ruine that comes <hi>thus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>this Way,</hi> then, we do no good; How, in what manner is it, that, in bearing all this, and by what we pay ſo deeply for, we are to <hi>make even</hi> with our Enemy, and <hi>more</hi> than ſo? How is <hi>he</hi> to be made come off at length the greateſt Sufferer, in order to oblige him to yield? <hi>Where,</hi> if not <hi>here,</hi> are we to make the Impreſſion upon him that muſt give him <hi>the worſt</hi> in the War?</p>
            <p>There are none except thoſe who dream of <hi>a Deſcent;</hi> (which though but for the ſame Reaſons that made it laſt Year unſucceſsful, cannot be expected but to prove ſo this next, and is likely to prove more fatal to us, if ſo;) there are none, I ſay, except thoſe that under ſuch <hi>Councils,</hi> ſuch <hi>Miniſters</hi> intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſuch an <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> as ours, do flatter themſelves that <hi>a Deſcent</hi> ſhall be able to be made and be ſupported, ſo as to turn to the <hi>Enemy's</hi> Ruine and <hi>not our own;</hi> there are none beſides this ſort of Men, that go about confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to give any Hopes of Matters to be done by making an Impreſſion any where on <hi>France</hi> with our
<hi>Land-Armies.</hi> Which notwithſtanding, let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, ſince it is what we rely on. For being not in a way ſo much as to preſerve our ſelves at Sea; much leſs are we in the Deſign of ruining our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that way, deſtroying his Trade, and cutting off his Supply of Riches by which he bears up in the War: although indeed, thoſe very Riches come <hi>only</hi> into him by his Shipping, and the Exportations <hi>that way</hi> of his Country's Products: the Money that he gets for them in a <hi>Land-Trade,</hi> with any Country joining to him, being in compariſon very inconſiderable, and much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ballanc'd by the Charge he is at, in thoſe Countries, for many Neceſſities of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51030:6"/>his own, (eſpecially in War;) and by the vaſt Sums of Money continually diſtributed there in Penſions; as by conſidering only <hi>Switzerland,</hi> will plainly appear. But we, I ſay, do not apply our ſelves this way towards the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of <hi>France. To ruine him in his</hi> Weſt-India <hi>Trade, and cut him off his Sea-Men; To ſhut up his Commerce Northwards, through our own Seas; To ſpoil him</hi> (as might be) <hi>ſome of his chief Harbours and Sea-Port Towns; deſtroy the reſt of his Ships of Force, and ruine his Trading even in the</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean: This is what we either think not of at all, or think is inſignificant, or not ſo noble (nor ſo ſaving, or of diſpatch, it may be) as the Campaining Method at Land: Or as being leſs ſuitable to the Genius of <hi>our Prince,</hi> ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo leſs ſuitable to that of <hi>our Nation:</hi> Which, beſides, will be rais'd to high Eſteem and Power, and have its Liberties beſt guarded by the Eſtabliſhment of a Noble Army of its own, thus trained up; by that time they, join'd with the Foreigners, <hi>Dependents on our King,</hi> have made us victorious over the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and brought on for us our ſo wiſh'd-for
<hi>Peace,</hi> which <hi>then their Intereſt will endure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Sea</hi> therefore we leave as it is; and our Work being not to be done, or not convenient to our Preſent Court it ſhould be done, <hi>that way;</hi> our Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance is upon
<hi>another.</hi> Now to know how <hi>this Other</hi> is like to ſucceed with us; let us conſider in what Places of <hi>France</hi> it is that we may expect to make the Impreſſion
<hi>at Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hopes of <hi>Savoy</hi> are over. The ill Succeſs which that Attempt had at a time ſo advantageous, leaves indeed little to hope for any future time, after that this Baffle has given the <hi>French</hi> ſo great Security, cut off our Expectation from an Aſſiſtance of Proteſtants there, and given the occaſion to the <hi>French</hi> to put themſelves in another poſture on that ſide, ſtrengthen their Frontier, and ſecure thoſe Paſſages: and to do, at leaſt, <hi>ſo much</hi> for themſelves there; altho it were not likely that they ſhould be found to carry in a War this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer into <hi>Piedmont,</hi> that ſhall oblige that Prince to make his Terms.</p>
            <p>It is not on the <hi>Rhine</hi> ſurely, that we expect our <hi>Enemy</hi> ſhould be
<hi>Sufferer;</hi> when, inſtead of being put to uſe the Strength he has provided for his Defence there, he can every Year raiſe Contributions on that ſide ſufficient to maintain the Armies he imploys there; and take, with Countries, whole Regiments at a time; ſo as the Duke of
<hi>Wirtemberg</hi> and his Troops, were taken, lately, without ſo much as fighting, and about
3000 of the beſt <hi>German</hi> Horſe taken.</p>
            <p>We do not expect, I ſuppoſe, that an Army from <hi>Spain</hi> will enter <hi>France,</hi> or that that Nation is in a Condition to make an <hi>offenſive</hi> War againſt <hi>France.</hi> So that the <hi>ſtreſs</hi> of all lies now in <hi>Flanders.</hi> And do we expect to ſee ever any better Armies there, more numerous, more united, or more animated than they have been theſe laſt Campaigns? The Confederacy may ſoon be <hi>leſſer;</hi> But what can make it
<hi>greater?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51030:7"/>
            <p>Are we to find any other <hi>Generals</hi> of that Confederacy than what we have? Or will
<hi>theſe</hi> come to be abler, and out-grow the <hi>French</hi> ones at length by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience? If it be an Abſurdity to think thus; is it not a great one to think we ſhall have other
<hi>Succeſs</hi> than what we have had? And what has <hi>that</hi> been? At <hi>Flerus</hi> we receive a Rout, where we loſe a good Part of an Army. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Year, if we are not beat in the Campaign time, we are charg'd in the Rear, and a Mark given us at going off. <hi>Mons</hi> is taken one Year, and <hi>Namur</hi> the next; (with what Attendance is notorious.) So that if our ſtrongeſt Towns, we ſee, go off before our ſtrongeſt Armies; what are we to expect will be the Fate of the other Towns that are as yet remaining with us, and are the laſt that keep the
<hi>Barrier?</hi> They too, if not immediately, muſt in a Campaign or two more, go the ſame way of courſe: though at the cloſing of our Campaigns (which cannot keep us up <hi>but a defenſive</hi> War) we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to take a kind of Revenge by attacquing the <hi>French</hi> with as much Advantage and Succeſs as we did now lately at <hi>Steinkirk.</hi> But can we think, notwithſtanding this, that by recruiting our waſted Troops, and by raiſing other n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w ones, proportionable to what <hi>France</hi> raiſes, we ſhall <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</hi> all this; and not only ſo, but after having retaken
<hi>Namur</hi> and <hi>Mons,</hi> with what elſe we have loſt, be able to pierce into
<hi>France</hi> through treble Ranks of Gariſons, by taking of them one by one, or all at once, or leaving 'em behind, and marching through 'em? Surely Men of thought will ſtick at this.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding all this; The Engagers with the Court, carrying a Majority in this Parliament with 'em, are giving the Government this inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Aſſiſtance, and are drawing from us vaſt Sums to ſupply Confederate Armies, and Armies of our own abroad: As if this were really to do us good, would avail any thing, and were our proper Method of ſecuring our ſelves; Whilſt our Sea-Practice (<hi>whence</hi> ſhould be drawn the <hi>French's</hi> Ruine, but
<hi>whence</hi> our own is now) lies in the ſhamefulleſt Condition that can be. What ſignifies it, that we have a number of huge Ships to ſail about toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Month or two in the Summer; if ſtill the <hi>French</hi> keep all they have in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and the Means that they have there (if not taken from 'em) of breeding Sea-Men, above all the World beſides; if here, in <hi>our</hi> Seas, they breed vaſt Numbers, and ſet out numerous and mighty Ships out of the ſpoil of us and our Ships? If Trading be not ſafe for <hi>us;</hi> our Seas being <hi>to us</hi> ſhut up, and <hi>Sweeds, Danes, Portugees,</hi> and other Nations to whom the Sea is free, growing into Trade, and carrying all Supplies (which <hi>thus</hi> we cannot hinder) into <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis plain, that if we cannot after this, we certainly muſt ſink. 'Tis againſt
<hi>this,</hi> that we ſhould turn all our Power, our Riches; which would not then be doubly loſt in being <hi>given amongst Foreigners,</hi> from <hi>England,</hi> never to return
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51030:7"/>thither; and being <hi>given</hi> beſides, <hi>in vain.</hi> 'Tis towards
<hi>this</hi> we ſhould turn all our Care and Counſels; and therefore, if the <hi>good Genius</hi> of <hi>England</hi> has not Power enough, by Patriots within it, to alter this Adminiſtration, all is in vain, and we muſt fall.</p>
            <p>That, <hi>in this reſpect,</hi> we do <hi>now</hi> every thing ſo improperly, every thing ſo waſtfully that we pretend to do; and that there is ſo little a Part aimed at or intended, of what might farther be done by us than is attempted under the preſent Management; there is indeed no wonder. When of all Parts of our Government, there is not any more looſe, more inconſiſtent, more corrupt, than that Part which regards our Sea-Affair. We have no Council, no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for Trade eſtabliſh'd, nothing of any Office inſtituted, or Officers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly qualified and empower'd to inſpect our Trade, to report the Condition of it, and propoſe the Regulations neceſſary, to our Parliament; inſomuch, that <hi>that Aſſembly</hi> is forc'd, upon Occaſions, to have recourſe to the Merchants themſelves, to be inſtructed, and are often at a loſs, and (as in the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Buſineſs) in a likelihood of ruining Trade, by having their only Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in thoſe <hi>nice</hi> Matters from ſuch as are ſurely intereſted one way or ther. Our Offices of Admiralty and the like, are diſpos'd of in Gifts to Men of Intrigue: and (as the World has now ſufficiently remark'd) he that by his Skill can work a Party, delay or bring on a Buſineſs in the Parliament, and has the
<hi>Houſe-Craft,</hi> is recommended to the ſteering of a Fleet, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of our Naval Force. All is of a peice; and throughout all the Places, any ways relating to this <hi>great Truſt,</hi> down to the very inferiour Officers, in ſingle Ships, <hi>Bribery</hi> and
<hi>Cabal</hi> does every thing.</p>
            <p>If this go on, as has been ſhewn, <hi>England ſinks,</hi> whoever <hi>riſes;</hi> We are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the laſt Miſery, and a Foundation, at this rate, is laying for ſuch <hi>a State</hi> as was before repreſented. And <hi>now,</hi> at this preſent time, if the Houſe of Commons carry not what they have begun upon the Admiralty, to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al thorough Reformation in all
<hi>thoſe</hi> Affairs, however <hi>the others</hi> are ſuffer'd to lie; if our Force at Sea, and the natural Strength that way, which we have yet left amongſt us, be not by their ordering otherwiſe exerted; other-gueſs Encouragements ſet up for Sea-Men; the <hi>Sea Souldiering,</hi> the very <hi>Vocation</hi> it ſelf, by a better Uſage of thoſe that follow
<hi>it,</hi> made more advantageous than as <hi>it</hi> now ſtands, that <hi>it</hi> may draw in more than <hi>any other,</hi> and not be, as <hi>it</hi> is, the moſt juſtly declinable, and ready to be abandon'd by thoſe that are already in; if there be not an other-gueſs rewarding of thoſe that ſerve well; the proper Methods ſet up to clear us of the <hi>French-Cruiſers, and their Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers;</hi> fit Ships, with right Regulation, apply'd to that Work; The Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with <hi>them</hi> not left (ſo as it now is) as an ungrateful Work only, but the Reducing of them made (by Rewards fitted to ſuch Service, as well for Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateers and Adventurers of our own, as for the Ships of the Publick) an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51030:8"/>moſt advantageous, and which may be heartily undertaken by thoſe that ſo expoſe themſelves; <hi>In ſhort,</hi> what-ever ill Performance, Unskilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Corruption be ſuffered in any other Part of our Government; How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Matters may go in
<hi>Weſtminſter-Hall;</hi> however the Chancery be filled, or any Offices in the
<hi>Nation</hi> that are to do Right amongſt Particulars of <hi>that Body;</hi> however any other Part of the Miniſtry ſtand, according to whatſoever Party; <hi>If</hi> our Parliament do not now <hi>right</hi> our Country in this Concern; do not <hi>redreſs</hi> and <hi>aſſure this part</hi> of our Adminiſtration, in Hands they can intruſt, and ſhall have Power over to make Faithful; and by <hi>their own Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement</hi> (for it will be by no other) ſave thus what we are loſing not only to the French, but to all other Foreigners that uſe the Sea; If they do not
<hi>thus much,</hi> and ſuddenly ſet us in another Courſe to regain what's paſt, and do our utmoſt <hi>here;</hi> However great theſe <hi>Armies</hi> and <hi>Confederacies</hi> ſound, that fill ſo many Heads at preſent; whatever <hi>Pomp</hi> and <hi>Grandeur</hi> in this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment hinders them from dreaming any Inſecurity in it; I fear they will not long be Poſſeſſors of the Power that accompanies them now in their Seats at
<hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> nor be the Maſters long of thoſe Eſtates that give them now the Places they have there. Their giving Millions ſo liberally, will but haſten the Buſineſs: though many give their Concurrence to this moſt unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident way of giving, and to the Methods proportionable, of raiſing what is thus given: not as unſenſible of Miſmanagement; but out of meer Fear of being over-run. But it is ordinary to ſee Men in their Fears run more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly upon their Ruine; when terrified they ſtrive moſt earneſtly to avoid it. Yet if they would act rationally, according to what they fear, why is not <hi>the Fleet</hi> firſt ſecured? why is not <hi>that Money</hi> firſt found out, ſecured on the beſt Funds, and well appropriated, that the Money <hi>really</hi> given to <hi>that</hi> may not leaſt ſerve <hi>that purpoſe;</hi> that it may not run a common risk with the other Money expected to be raiſed; nor the <hi>neceſſary</hi> Charge of our Navy run the ſame Danger of being unſupplied, as any of thoſe <hi>exorbitant</hi> and <hi>unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> Charges we are to be at beſides? What if there be found Stops and Difficulties; if the Money fails for <hi>theſe latter</hi> Expences, muſt it fail too for our <hi>Great</hi> and perhaps <hi>only neceſſary</hi> Expence, that of our Ships and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men?</p>
            <p>What-ever be, this muſt be look'd to. And (to join all to what I have ſhown before) he that is <hi>an Engliſh-man</hi> in any Party, and forgets <hi>this,</hi> knows not that he is drawing-on his own and Countries Ruine, in the Proſpect of eſtabliſhing his Country by means of that Party, or together with that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty's Intereſt which he follows: for though a Peace ſhould be concluded at laſt, according to the Scope of K. <hi>James</hi>'s Party, by which
<hi>that</hi> King ſhould be made to be acknowledged; or though the Adherents to K.
<hi>William</hi> that are ſupporting him <hi>his Way,</hi> ſhould ſee him prevailing with his
<hi>Land-Forces,</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51030:8"/>
               <hi>France</hi> reduc'd to ſuch a Peace as ſhould cauſe the Acknowledgment of King <hi>William</hi> here; yet at the end of all this, if by <hi>that time,</hi> the Work that is now doing apace be brought to its effect, and we left <hi>Inferiours</hi> at Sea, cheated and beaten out of our Trade, and periſh'd in our <hi>Naval Power,</hi> with nothing but a Power
<hi>at Land</hi> to defend us: All the Advantage that the Party of <hi>Engliſh Men</hi> then prevailing will obtain, beſides their Triumph, or their Revenge over their Adverſaries, will be to hold a <hi>Government</hi> under the Force of a Foreigner, and <hi>which</hi> can be held no otherwiſe; and to give us ever after for a Government, that which ſhall be enforc'd by the Nation, or Prince left with the ſtrongeſt Force abroad, together with the Honour of being thenceforward conſtantly the <hi>Teſt</hi> of Power and Precedency to the contending States of
<hi>Europe,</hi> by falling always to <hi>their</hi> Lot who can force others hence, and place themſelves.</p>
            <p>Now if there be any <hi>Engliſh-Man</hi> in theſe Parties, that will <hi>thoroughly</hi> think; I appeal to him, if what we do <hi>all-together</hi> in Parliament, or what <hi>each Party</hi> drives at <hi>ſingly,</hi> is like to bring any Happineſs to one, whoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is <hi>England.</hi> If the removing one Miniſtry for another; the getting Men, or keeping Men in place for only Party-Merits: The <hi>driving</hi> in the common Manner, for the Intereſt of
<hi>this</hi> Court or <hi>that;</hi> for <hi>the Court now undermoſt,</hi> by endeavouring to embroil our Sea-Affairs, bring us Loſs of Trade and Ruine of Shipping, that by ſuch Miſery the People may (as thoſe think) be induc'd to abandon this Government: And <hi>for the Intereſt of the Preſent Court;</hi> by complying with any ſort of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods it takes, however cenſur'd at other times; by advancing Prerogative at a time which is the only Ever to be hop'd for to bring it down from its Encroachments, and to confirm the Rights of the People, which are hardly ſupportable under the Weight yet left in ſome Fundamental Points: By gaining Acts for multiplying of Treaſons, inſtead of ſecuring us from the Power that the Crown now has of making Treaſon too eaſily out of any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: By the juſtifying any Commitments as well as Trials; the ſetting on foot (to a vexatious End, and no other) <hi>needleſs</hi> ſevere Oaths, ſo extenſive and generally to be enforc'd, for the Puniſhment only of Mens Conſciences, or the taking away of all Conſcience, ſo as to loſe the Benefit of all Oaths in any Caſe; <hi>a Thing</hi> ſo deſtructive to all Government, and (to our great Miſery) begun already to be felt amongſt us, and encreaſing daily by the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that Oaths are expos'd to, in ſerving every Turn. In fine, By the giving away all our Wealth to the Managers of the Court in <hi>prodigious Sums;</hi> ſuch as, if poſſible, would ſuffice their Greedineſs, and ſurmount their Laviſhment; whilſt ſtill the Matters of <hi>our</hi> Ocean (that Ocean that ſhould be ours) ſtand <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
